<?xml version="1.0"?>
<post heading="Heroes and Villains" permalink="heroes-and-villains" date="2014-07-25 20:40">

<html>
<script type="text/javascript" src="http://localhost/heroes-and-villains/h.js">1</script>
<table class="image-left" style="margin-right:10px">
<caption class="image-caption" style="text-align:center;padding-right:10px;">
Demo runs for 5 seconds then pauses (so as to not drain your laptop's battery).
Click the demo to resume. Subsequent clicks restart the demo.
</caption>
<tr><td>
<canvas id="hs" style="position:relative" width="400" height="400">Your browser does not support canvas.</canvas>
</td></tr>
</table>

</html>

This is an explanation of a graphical demo I call "Heroes and Villains".
I wrote the [first version](/hero) in my first year of university and it was one of the
first demos on this site. I revisited the code several years later when I entered
a modified version for the [JS1K](http://js1k.com/2014-dragons/demo/1905)
and realized that I made a fundamental mathematical error in the first version,
but fixing the error caused it to be less interesting to watch so I re-implemented the bug
as a "feature". But more on that later.

## Entomology
The demo is named after a "getting to know you" game.
Take a room full of people and tell each of them to choose one person to be their "hero",
and choose a second person to be their "villain", keeping the identity of both a secret.
Then tell each person to move such that their hero is between themselves, and their villain.
As each person moves into position, they force other people to keep moving, as the position of
each person affects the position of people who have chosen them as heroes or villains.
Played indoors in groups of around 15, people tend to stand in lines moving sideways or radially about the
centre of the room, and tend to also move outwards getting as close to walls as possible.

Naturally, the question arises: "Will the system ever reach a stable state, where everyone's hero is between
themselves and their villain?" This demo started out as an attempt to simulate the game with
a large number of players in a large space over a large period.

</post>
